Leah: Background, ethnicity, and
culture can strongly influence beliefs
about mental illness and shapes
attitudes towards the mentally ill,
let’s look at some of these factors.
Social status and the concept of
saving ‘face’ in Asian communities
is very important and a mental health
issue may cause public embarrassment
and could damage reputations, this
may subsequently affect marriage
prospects or business transactions.
Therefore, those who are suffering,
and their families are less
likely to seek a diagnosis.
Most cultures discourage males from
showing physical or mental weakness.
Whilst western countries are now
leaning more to encouraging males
to seek help, and admit to needing
support, many still remain resistant
as this may show inadequacy especially
in more male dominated cultures.
Not every culture trusts western
medical practices, instead they prefer
to use traditional methods and often
don’t see mental health as medical,
but spiritual involving evil spirits.
Some South American cultures believe
in the evil eye and don’t talk about
mental health issues for fear of
being labeled as “locos” or crazy
Buddhism and Taoism advocate
spiritual understanding and believe
mental health problems are a result
of bad deeds in previous lives.
Every culture has its own way of
making sense of mental health and each
culture has its opinion on whether
mental illness is real or imagined,
an illness of the mind or the body or
both, who is at risk for it, what might
cause it, and perhaps most importantly,
the level of stigma surrounding it.
Younger people in all cultures are
more likely to seek help, but older
people especially those from other
countries and cultures, are less likely
to change their behaviour and attitude.
This can cause problems and divisions
in families regarding seeking a
diagnosis either restricting them
or making them break from tradition
and subsequently the family.